<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:content='http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<title>Medium Archive</title>
<link>https://charltonesque.github.io/medium-archive/</link>
<description>Imported posts</description>
<language>en-us</language>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 22:50:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
<atom:link href='https://charltonesque.github.io/medium-archive/rss-2.xml' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml' />
<item>
<title>Why Do Strategy, Anyway?</title>
<link>https://charltonesque.github.io/medium-archive/posts/2021-09-27_Why-Do-Strategy--Anyway--355e0e760861.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://charltonesque.github.io/medium-archive/posts/2021-09-27_Why-Do-Strategy--Anyway--355e0e760861.html</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 07:10:41 +0000</pubDate>
<description>Playing To Win Why Do Strategy, Anyway? To Learn Faster to Win Source: PC Vey, Cartoon Stock The first 51 posts of the Playing to Win/Practitioner Insights (PTW/PI) series have concerned how to do str</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<section class="section section--body section--first section--last" name="4e68"><div class="section-divider"><hr class="section-divider"/></div><div class="section-content"><div class="section-inner sectionLayout--insetColumn"><h4 class="graf graf--h4 graf--leading graf--kicker" id="4aed" name="4aed">Playing To Win</h4><h3 class="graf graf--h3 graf-after--h4 graf--title" id="0649" name="0649">Why Do Strategy, Anyway?</h3><h4 class="graf graf--h4 graf-after--h3 graf--subtitle" id="037a" name="037a">To Learn Faster to Win</h4><figure class="graf graf--figure graf-after--h4" id="ade1" name="ade1"><img class="graf-image" data-height="1753" data-image-id="1*YoS9lts-NNFzI-WGQg5X1Q.jpeg" data-is-featured="true" data-width="2008" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*YoS9lts-NNFzI-WGQg5X1Q.jpeg"/><figcaption class="imageCaption">Source: PC Vey, Cartoon Stock</figcaption></figure><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--figure" id="3dda" name="3dda">The first 51 posts of the Playing to Win/Practitioner Insights (PTW/PI) series have concerned <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">how</em> <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">to do</em> strategy. I thought it would be fun to do one on <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">whether</em> <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">to do</em> strategy. Many executives aren’t convinced that it is a worthwhile endeavor. And they could interpret some of the things I say about strategy as supportive of that view. So, to achieve clarity, I have dedicated my 52nd PTW/PI on the question: Why Do Strategy, Anyway? The answer is: To Learn Faster to Win. (Links for the rest of the PTW/PI series can be found <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogerlmartin.com/archive/medium-posts" href="https://rogerlmartin.com/archive/medium-posts" rel="noopener" target="_blank">here</a>.)</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="4cc7" name="4cc7"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">The Case Against Strategy</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="a618" name="a618">The case against strategy is mainly framed as an issue of favoring practicality and action-orientation over theory and esoterica. I have observed four lines of reasoning underpinning this view. First is an undertone of: ‘tough guys/gals don’t do strategy. Strategy is for executives who like to talk and have meetings rather than take action.’ Second is an obsession with ‘execution,’ whatever that is, and a belief that somehow time spent on ‘strategy’ is time taken away from ‘execution.’ This is something I have written about repeatedly — <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://hbr.org/2010/07/the-execution-trap" href="https://hbr.org/2010/07/the-execution-trap" rel="noopener" target="_blank">here</a>, <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://hbr.org/2015/03/stop-distinguishing-between-execution-and-strategy" href="https://hbr.org/2015/03/stop-distinguishing-between-execution-and-strategy" rel="noopener" target="_blank">here</a>, <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://hbr.org/2015/09/why-talking-about-strategy-execution-is-still-dangerous" href="https://hbr.org/2015/09/why-talking-about-strategy-execution-is-still-dangerous" rel="noopener" target="_blank">here</a>, and <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://hbr.org/2016/01/strategy-and-execution-are-the-same-thing" href="https://hbr.org/2016/01/strategy-and-execution-are-the-same-thing" rel="noopener" target="_blank">here</a> for example. Third is that they don’t have time for strategy because their business is so fast-moving — which I have also <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/my-business-is-too-fast-moving-for-strategy-bf3132d0c994" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/my-business-is-too-fast-moving-for-strategy-bf3132d0c994" rel="noopener" target="_blank">written about</a>.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="758d" name="758d">Fourth is to interpret the work of great management thinkers as arguing against strategy. It is most common to quote the greatest management thinker in history, Peter Drucker, dissing strategy by saying: “Culture eats strategy for breakfast.” The Drucker Institute has determined through a big archival research project that Drucker never said such a thing and recently issued a <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://www.drucker.institute/did-peter-drucker-say-that/" href="https://www.drucker.institute/did-peter-drucker-say-that/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">definitive statement</a> to that effect. Nonetheless, the quote continues to be used as if Drucker actually said it.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="ab08" name="ab08">The other misused scholar is the first great Canadian management scholar, Henry Mintzberg, who introduced the concept of ‘emergent strategy.’ Mintzberg observed that because managers can’t predict the future accurately enough to have their strategy play out entirely as planned, what they actually do is often at odds with their proclaimed strategy. Instead, they make numerous course corrections in the face of substantial changes in their competitive environment. Mintzberg’s purpose was to encourage managers not to assume that they could stick rigidly with their ‘deliberate strategy’ but rather recognize that they would have to tweak their strategy to take into account unforeseen weaknesses that emerge in it.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="c3e7" name="c3e7">I agree with Mintzberg (on this and many other things). However, many executives have taken emergent strategy to mean that since the future is so volatile and unpredictable, it doesn’t make sense to waste time on strategy until such time as the future becomes clear. For fun, I will ask them how will they be able to judge the point at which volatility becomes low enough and predictability high enough to start making choices? I have never gotten a good answer to that question. That notwithstanding, this line of reasoning has become the rationale for the ‘fast follower’ approach that many executives tell me proudly they are using. They just wait for someone to start doing something successful and then hop on that train. In this way, Mintzberg’s emergent strategy concept, like Drucker’s misquote, is misused to justify not doing strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="292e" name="292e">Executives also could use some of my views on strategy to buttress the case against. I clearly argue that you can’t predict the future and can never be certain in advance that your chosen strategy is ‘right.’ And I maintain that the best a strategy can do is shorten the odds of success. It can’t guarantee success. They may take these views of mine as arguments against strategy even though they are most certainly not.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="1b09" name="1b09">All of these lines of reasoning in combination make it appealing to many executives to think that it is best to be a fast follower focusing on executing rather than wasting time on strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="e4fc" name="e4fc"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">The Case For Strategy</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="93eb" name="93eb">For me, the case for strategy centers on learning. I believe that doing strategy thoroughly and religiously is the key to gaining a learning advantage over competition.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="e2f1" name="e2f1">The way to maximize learning in strategy is to use all your current knowledge to develop a hypothesis as to the most compelling strategy choice, then enact it, and then observe the degree to which things turn out the way you expected, then, based on those observations, develop a next generation hypothesis, which you put into action, and then observe and learn again. And so on. If you repeatedly go through that learning loop rigorously and, importantly, faster than your competitors, you will maximize your chance of ending up on top.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="d837" name="d837">This is, must assuredly, not my idea. It is borrowed from what most insiders would consider the greatest air combat theoretician in history, the late Air Force Colonel John Boyd, creator of the OODA (observe, orient, decide, act) Loop. Boyd argued that if a fighter pilot rigorously goes through the OODA Loop faster than his enemy, he will maximize the probability of beating the enemy in air combat. The key is the combination — rigor in each step; and getting through more cycles of the OODA Loop faster than the enemy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="2c3f" name="2c3f">If instead, while your competition is engaging in that learning activity, you wait to see what emerges in order to fast-follow, you will always be playing catch-up on the knowledge necessary to compete, and in due course, per Boyd, you will be shot down.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="739d" name="739d">The thinking loop doesn’t have to use a formal strategic planning process or strategy language. What matters is the thinking. I learned more about strategy from my father than I have from anyone else. He has only a technical high school education and started an animal feed manufacturing business at 27 years old (when I was two years old), long before a thing called business strategy existed.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="a29a" name="a29a">Growing up, I quizzed him incessantly about the business. There was always a highly reasoned answer. <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">Our feed delivery trucks are pristinely washed multiple times a day as necessary to connote to farmers that there will be no breakdowns and late deliveries. We never sell at any price other than our published price list — that way sales calls will be about service/quality not about negotiating price.</em> The strategic reasoning was always crystal clear — even without what I now know as strategy language.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="a852" name="a852">Because of this experience, I am an enthusiast of simple (not simplistic) and practical strategy. I am not a fan of big words and mega-concepts. But I always insist on a thesis concerning the industry, customers, our company, and competitors to underpin the set of choices being made. And then watch and adjust accordingly, again, and again.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="03d8" name="03d8">The payoff is that you get to start working on answering important strategy questions before your competitors realize that they are questions. I have had the privilege of working for many companies that are at the top of their respective fields. One thing they have in common is that they ask questions before competitors even think about the broad category in which the question resides. Consequently, they don’t have to be better or faster at solving customer problems because they get to start work long before their competitors. That is, they have been through more OODA loops than their competitors at any given point in time. Was P&amp;G awesome at developing and rolling out the fantastically successful Tide Pods? In truth not really. The manufacturing build up and roll out of Pods was fraught with problems. But that didn’t really matter because competitors only figured out what was coming mere months prior to the launch as word of the Pods launch filtered out. But that was years after P&amp;G had started work on the project. It gave P&amp;G plenty of time to get the manufacturing of Tide Pods down to a science. Competition, which was numerous OODA Loops behind, didn’t have a chance.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="248a" name="248a">Outflanking your competitors means learning faster than them. The fastest and most effective way of learning is to form a theory, act on the theory, observe the deviations from predictions of the theory, and then adjust accordingly — and then do it again. You can’t do that and won’t do it if you don’t think strategy is worth doing.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="56ad" name="56ad"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">Practitioner Insights</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="0341" name="0341">Business is tricky and daunting. You are always in a position of needing to make decisions today for a tomorrow that will always be uncertain. And even if you don’t think of yourself as making choices, no choice is actually a choice — because <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/strategy-is-what-you-do-not-what-you-say-a6e483840557" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/strategy-is-what-you-do-not-what-you-say-a6e483840557" rel="noopener" target="_blank">strategy is what you do, not what you say</a>. But don’t be intimidated by the challenge. You don’t have to be perfect. It is like the adage about the campers and the bear: you don’t have to outrun the bear, just your fellow campers! You just have to learn and get better at a faster rate than your competitors.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="637a" name="637a">The worst thing you can do is sit and wait until it is clear which competitor is winning and in what way before you take action. But there is a danger at the other end of the spectrum in over-intellectualizing in a vain attempt to be perfect. Players at both ends of the spectrum have slower OODA Loops than competitors in the middle.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p graf--trailing" id="343f" name="343f">You should think hard but expeditiously. Place your strategic bet. Then watch and learn. Tweak it if it is close; reboot if it isn’t. Do it again, and again. And that will be your advantage over your competitors who learn more slowly. It will especially be the case relative to those who watch what works for you and then imitate it. You will be gone by the time they get to where you used to be. And that is the fundamental advantage of doing strategy over making excuses for why you don’t!</p></div></div></section>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Year of Strategy</title>
<link>https://charltonesque.github.io/medium-archive/posts/2021-10-04_A-Year-of-Strategy-7a4bc4222134.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://charltonesque.github.io/medium-archive/posts/2021-10-04_A-Year-of-Strategy-7a4bc4222134.html</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 13:01:32 +0000</pubDate>
<description>Playing to Win A Year of Strategy A Playing to Win/Practitioner Insights Retrospective Copyright: Roger L. Martin, 2021 It all started innocently. I was getting frustrated with how long it took to get</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<section class="section section--body section--first section--last" name="06ce"><div class="section-divider"><hr class="section-divider"/></div><div class="section-content"><div class="section-inner sectionLayout--insetColumn"><h4 class="graf graf--h4 graf--leading graf--kicker" id="01d0" name="01d0">Playing to Win</h4><h3 class="graf graf--h3 graf-after--h4 graf--title" id="08b7" name="08b7">A Year of Strategy</h3><h4 class="graf graf--h4 graf-after--h3 graf--subtitle" id="e2b0" name="e2b0">A Playing to Win/Practitioner Insights Retrospective</h4><figure class="graf graf--figure graf-after--h4" id="974b" name="974b"><img class="graf-image" data-height="480" data-image-id="1*4nXDbzqxXXRewm1NoPWoBw.gif" data-is-featured="true" data-width="853" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*4nXDbzqxXXRewm1NoPWoBw.gif"/><figcaption class="imageCaption">Copyright: Roger L. Martin, 2021</figcaption></figure><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--figure" id="8cf0" name="8cf0">It all started innocently. I was getting frustrated with how long it took to get quick hit writing out. For what are hoped to be timeless pieces for the print edition of Harvard Business Review, I don’t mind the one to three years it takes to get an article ready for publication. But I had a time-sensitive piece on COVID and strategy that I submitted to a faster-cycle publication (that shall remain nameless) in the summer of 2020 when companies were desperately trying to figure out how to navigate COVID. The editor liked it but told me that it would be at least three weeks until she would even look at a full draft.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="e3da" name="e3da">I groused about that lackadaisical reaction to Jessica Krakoski, who was helping with the publicity of my fall 2020 book, <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">When More is Not Better</em>. She suggested that I experiment with writing for Medium because on that platform, the minute you have finished writing a piece, you can hit ‘publish’ and it is out there. I followed her suggestion (thanks Jessica!) and on July 23, 2020, published <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://medium.com/me/stats/post/8d3ad00b8cd7" href="https://medium.com/me/stats/post/8d3ad00b8cd7" target="_blank">Habits, COVID &amp; Strategy</a>. I enjoyed my first Medium experience and wrote another nine pieces on a variety of subjects.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="bf67" name="bf67">Then, in response to a client’s question, I wrote <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fthe-innovation%2fthe-role-of-management-systems-in-strategy-571583546fbe&amp;c=E,1,rYhIq-8Evi2Vq5tSyG19bK3ybrul9gKaBLPHlnDuwybBnOP6hBL05MsttJEzO4b92aCGLZTUaE0ULyQ0U-87KEkqrykfv6ddC4ZN0yXu0oQeF6jFLA,,&amp;typo=1" href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fthe-innovation%2fthe-role-of-management-systems-in-strategy-571583546fbe&amp;c=E,1,rYhIq-8Evi2Vq5tSyG19bK3ybrul9gKaBLPHlnDuwybBnOP6hBL05MsttJEzO4b92aCGLZTUaE0ULyQ0U-87KEkqrykfv6ddC4ZN0yXu0oQeF6jFLA,,&amp;typo=1" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fthe-innovation%2fthe-role-of-management-systems-in-strategy-571583546fbe&amp;c=E,1,rYhIq-8Evi2Vq5tSyG19bK3ybrul9gKaBLPHlnDuwybBnOP6hBL05MsttJEzO4b92aCGLZTUaE0ULyQ0U-87KEkqrykfv6ddC4ZN0yXu0oQeF6j">The Role of Management Systems in Strategy</a> to provide practical advice on how to think about the fifth box in my Strategy Choice Cascade, and published it on October 5, 2020. The response was so overwhelming that I decided to write more pieces for <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">Playing to Win</em> enthusiasts who wanted tips on how to apply the framework in practice. The series built a momentum of its own and an increasingly large audience. I established a weekly rhythm and published one Playing to Win/Practitioner Insights (PTW/PI) piece every Monday morning for 52 consecutive weeks: <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">A Year of Strategy</em>.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="4bc9" name="4bc9">I will first recap the year and then provide thoughts on where from here?</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="3a10" name="3a10"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">A Recap of <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">A Year of Strategy</em></strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="4bc4" name="4bc4">1) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fthe-innovation%2fthe-role-of-management-systems-in-strategy-571583546fbe&amp;c=E,1,rYhIq-8Evi2Vq5tSyG19bK3ybrul9gKaBLPHlnDuwybBnOP6hBL05MsttJEzO4b92aCGLZTUaE0ULyQ0U-87KEkqrykfv6ddC4ZN0yXu0oQeF6jFLA,,&amp;typo=1" href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fthe-innovation%2fthe-role-of-management-systems-in-strategy-571583546fbe&amp;c=E,1,rYhIq-8Evi2Vq5tSyG19bK3ybrul9gKaBLPHlnDuwybBnOP6hBL05MsttJEzO4b92aCGLZTUaE0ULyQ0U-87KEkqrykfv6ddC4ZN0yXu0oQeF6jFLA,,&amp;typo=1" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fthe-innovation%2fthe-role-of-management-systems-in-strategy-571583546fbe&amp;c=E,1,rYhIq-8Evi2Vq5tSyG19bK3ybrul9gKaBLPHlnDuwybBnOP6hBL05MsttJEzO4b92aCGLZTUaE0ULyQ0U-87KEkqrykfv6ddC4ZN0yXu0oQeF6j">The Role of Management Systems in Strategy</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="62f9" name="62f9">The three important roles Management Systems can play in reinforcing strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="1d55" name="1d55">2) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fthe-innovation%2fis-the-opposite-of-your-choice-stupid-on-its-face-5b247ffd7f94&amp;c=E,1,NVRyvwrRet6MR_c1K4oP32J9shr_s3HXD5fJce-ziDiKpffbO6g3rCKS0BaJDj6fim6WabMcPk3Eq8EzalXxhcZFE042suHPrg-DUDS0lTmQI67NsvmYkXEISg,,&amp;typo=1" href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fthe-innovation%2fis-the-opposite-of-your-choice-stupid-on-its-face-5b247ffd7f94&amp;c=E,1,NVRyvwrRet6MR_c1K4oP32J9shr_s3HXD5fJce-ziDiKpffbO6g3rCKS0BaJDj6fim6WabMcPk3Eq8EzalXxhcZFE042suHPrg-DUDS0lTmQI67NsvmYkXEISg,,&amp;typo=1" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="https://medium.com/the-innovation/is-the-opposite-of-your-choice-stupid-on-its-face-5b247ffd7f94">Is the Opposite of Your Choice Stupid on its Face?</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="5b85" name="5b85">You will know that you have made a strategy choice if the opposite is not stupid on its face.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="bdb2" name="bdb2">3) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fan-idea%2fwhy-i-am-skeptical-of-low-market-shares-a65e65911dce&amp;c=E,1,opJ0tq-8LBGoErbUJWbe_73Ek7zMgAwni5k2etyjRNRyF8j35DDXNdR5RJX2KSkAcgtRGEq4fK60zdvLh4av5wLpnBqRPIdSjeZrc-DZAV1pcSZzdQ,,&amp;typo=1" href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fan-idea%2fwhy-i-am-skeptical-of-low-market-shares-a65e65911dce&amp;c=E,1,opJ0tq-8LBGoErbUJWbe_73Ek7zMgAwni5k2etyjRNRyF8j35DDXNdR5RJX2KSkAcgtRGEq4fK60zdvLh4av5wLpnBqRPIdSjeZrc-DZAV1pcSZzdQ,,&amp;typo=1" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="https://medium.com/an-idea/why-i-am-skeptical-of-low-market-shares-a65e65911dce">Why I am Skeptical of Low Market Shares</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="56b3" name="56b3">If you think your market share is under 20%, you probably have defined the denominator too broadly.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="e7a7" name="e7a7">4) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fan-idea%2fstrategy-is-what-you-do-not-what-you-say-a6e483840557&amp;c=E,1,GvJRYiKC-B8Z6outBUQA-mRMd2qTujPwO3DY2nAsGri6gns_fv-SyPUQqxfHPvKjtf1Rxlei9iT4wOA9lagubiqxZCyDCGL8SUs0cfMY1w,,&amp;typo=1" href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fan-idea%2fstrategy-is-what-you-do-not-what-you-say-a6e483840557&amp;c=E,1,GvJRYiKC-B8Z6outBUQA-mRMd2qTujPwO3DY2nAsGri6gns_fv-SyPUQqxfHPvKjtf1Rxlei9iT4wOA9lagubiqxZCyDCGL8SUs0cfMY1w,,&amp;typo=1" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="https://medium.com/an-idea/strategy-is-what-you-do-not-what-you-say-a6e483840557">Strategy is what you Do, not what you Say</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="6f49" name="6f49">It is more helpful to understand your strategy as what you do than what it says in any strategic plan, and therefore every organization has a strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="1cb3" name="1cb3">5) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2froger-78069.medium.com%2fstrategy-as-problem-solving-5c6fb9291d87&amp;c=E,1,gORdeAgfcOouQTONtG6Gvd75Lb2VxdMTpvIjuNCfrx08F0IyBt7n2Qo1s83AMOjvuUABC2qwJkRtFMM_YEZIAzmfjnrY_mgFgONmBTHUVWGMyXXxOTQLUSa44Q,,&amp;typo=1" href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2froger-78069.medium.com%2fstrategy-as-problem-solving-5c6fb9291d87&amp;c=E,1,gORdeAgfcOouQTONtG6Gvd75Lb2VxdMTpvIjuNCfrx08F0IyBt7n2Qo1s83AMOjvuUABC2qwJkRtFMM_YEZIAzmfjnrY_mgFgONmBTHUVWGMyXXxOTQLUSa44Q,,&amp;typo=1" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="https://roger-78069.medium.com/strategy-as-problem-solving-5c6fb9291d87">Strategy as Problem-Solving</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="bc4b" name="bc4b">Strategy is a technique for solving problems. If you don’t define a problem to be solved, your strategy exercise is likely to have limited value.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="082e" name="082e">6) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fthe-innovation%2fstrategic-choice-chartering-3d56d8962ec3&amp;c=E,1,3Yjc2ILM5QbHMvbMgGNp9K4hqNGDUE1nacQKD_7ZnwnSMes-sqnyyM8EX9iciChdwhve8BvQhEqK-tdU2cqbAjP9RM4-_lvtHWLM_0PLkJEjiRarrsk_hFM,&amp;typo=1" href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2fmedium.com%2fthe-innovation%2fstrategic-choice-chartering-3d56d8962ec3&amp;c=E,1,3Yjc2ILM5QbHMvbMgGNp9K4hqNGDUE1nacQKD_7ZnwnSMes-sqnyyM8EX9iciChdwhve8BvQhEqK-tdU2cqbAjP9RM4-_lvtHWLM_0PLkJEjiRarrsk_hFM,&amp;typo=1" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="https://medium.com/the-innovation/strategic-choice-chartering-3d56d8962ec3">Strategic Choice Chartering</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="8b71" name="8b71">Strategy is created throughout the organization and hence the chartering of strategic choices is a very important leadership skill.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="5c5c" name="5c5c">7) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2froger-78069.medium.com%2ffrom-laudable-list-to-how-to-really-win-6aa20498e89&amp;c=E,1,IhHDdvdmKGqa92bZfjz9LOOrvdkkhmTIbw8AqCIhHH-CHAVYcSSeJ9sKHJVpoRRIccqe3IgUoDc_X9Yov3LBqqvPLwvpKKufX023JiAL3Q,,&amp;typo=1" href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2froger-78069.medium.com%2ffrom-laudable-list-to-how-to-really-win-6aa20498e89&amp;c=E,1,IhHDdvdmKGqa92bZfjz9LOOrvdkkhmTIbw8AqCIhHH-CHAVYcSSeJ9sKHJVpoRRIccqe3IgUoDc_X9Yov3LBqqvPLwvpKKufX023JiAL3Q,,&amp;typo=1" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="https://roger-78069.medium.com/from-laudable-list-to-how-to-really-win-6aa20498e89">From Laudable List to How to Really Win</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="93b3" name="93b3">Much of strategy involves making lists of laudable things to do but that don’t add up to a winning strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="9a92" name="9a92">8) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://medium.com/an-idea/strategy-as-a-practice-70a99a00735a" href="https://medium.com/an-idea/strategy-as-a-practice-70a99a00735a" target="_blank">Strategy as a Practice</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="838a" name="838a">Strategy is a practice and that the only way to get good at strategy is to practice the practice.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="4a06" name="4a06">9) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2froger-78069.medium.com%2fstrategy-time-a357865c1763&amp;c=E,1,uJT24g58EFwZswhzp307csKTtxlyXeRb-1ip_jKH6H6M-r00rlluwsa19omjX-QT066uFjuf9FQ_PXVetkN0CZWGi5ZdUOxXi2QBWmv5qOvm9fCACIY,&amp;typo=1" href="https://linkprotect.cudasvc.com/url?a=https%3a%2f%2froger-78069.medium.com%2fstrategy-time-a357865c1763&amp;c=E,1,uJT24g58EFwZswhzp307csKTtxlyXeRb-1ip_jKH6H6M-r00rlluwsa19omjX-QT066uFjuf9FQ_PXVetkN0CZWGi5ZdUOxXi2QBWmv5qOvm9fCACIY,&amp;typo=1" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Strategy &amp; Time</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="bcec" name="bcec">You should do strategy when your What Would Have to be True is no longer true, not on some calendar cycle.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="f62a" name="f62a">10) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/playing-to-win-for-social-sector-organizations-c3d948e17c67" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/playing-to-win-for-social-sector-organizations-c3d948e17c67" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="https://roger-78069.medium.com/playing-to-win-for-social-sector-organizations-c3d948e17c67">Playing to Win for Social Sector Organizations</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="a0f6" name="a0f6">How to apply Playing to Win to social sector organizations of all sorts.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="044b" name="044b">11) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/strategy-design-thinking-faf6b787160b" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/strategy-design-thinking-faf6b787160b" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Strategy &amp; Design Thinking</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="b8a9" name="b8a9">How to integrate key Design Thinking attributes into the Playing to Win strategy process.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="2134" name="2134">12) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/strategy-integrative-thinking-96ac0769709b" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/strategy-integrative-thinking-96ac0769709b" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Strategy &amp; Integrative Thinking</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="5f29" name="5f29">How key Integrative Thinking attributes can and should be integrated into the Playing to Win strategy process.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="81d8" name="81d8">13) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/on-the-inseparability-of-where-to-play-and-how-to-win-181c2ea5c463" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/on-the-inseparability-of-where-to-play-and-how-to-win-181c2ea5c463" rel="noopener" target="_blank">On the Inseparability of Where-to-Play and How-to-Win</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="ac32" name="ac32">Avoiding the trap of considering Where-to-Play and How-to-Win independently rather than in tandem.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="d0e2" name="d0e2">14) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/the-trap-of-presiding-over-strategy-63875df1e982" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/the-trap-of-presiding-over-strategy-63875df1e982" rel="noopener" target="_blank">The Trap of Presiding Over Strategy</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="959b" name="959b">Business leaders should not see their job as presiding over strategy but rather engaging deeply in strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="bbf2" name="bbf2">15) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/is-strategy-in-b2b-dramatically-different-than-in-b2c-98d25bc133e3" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/is-strategy-in-b2b-dramatically-different-than-in-b2c-98d25bc133e3" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Is Strategy in B2B Dramatically Different than in B2C?</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="2395" name="2395">There are more similarities than differences between B2C and B2B strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="d8bf" name="d8bf">16) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/my-business-is-too-fast-moving-for-strategy-bf3132d0c994" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/my-business-is-too-fast-moving-for-strategy-bf3132d0c994" rel="noopener" target="_blank">My Business is Too Fast-Moving for Strategy</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="055e" name="055e">It is both specious and dangerous to argue that your business is too fast-moving to do strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="b452" name="b452">17) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/playing-to-win-and-scenario-planning-e23f25f2a9c2" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/playing-to-win-and-scenario-planning-e23f25f2a9c2" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Playing to Win and Scenario Planning</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="a521" name="a521">How to integrate Scenario Planning attributes into the Playing to Win strategy process.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="fbf6" name="fbf6">18) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/distinguishing-how-to-win-from-capabilities-in-your-strategy-choice-fd190484ccea" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/distinguishing-how-to-win-from-capabilities-in-your-strategy-choice-fd190484ccea" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Distinguishing How-to-Win from Capabilities in Your Strategy Choice</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="7bb6" name="7bb6">How to untangle Capabilities from How-to-Win and think about Capabilities in the Strategy Choice Cascade.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="1623" name="1623">19) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/the-two-rules-that-monopolists-ignore-at-their-peril-e26b1a9f0ca7" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/the-two-rules-that-monopolists-ignore-at-their-peril-e26b1a9f0ca7" rel="noopener" target="_blank">The Two Rules that Monopolists Ignore at Their Peril</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="5532" name="5532">This was the least successful of the 52 posts. Must not have felt sufficiently practitioner focused, but it identifies important watchouts for monopolies.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="7bb8" name="7bb8">20) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/strategy-vs-planning-complements-not-substitutes-ea08e56809d6" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/strategy-vs-planning-complements-not-substitutes-ea08e56809d6" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Strategy vs. Planning: Complements not Substitutes</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="72dd" name="72dd">The second most read post provides the key distinction between Strategy and Planning.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="29d6" name="29d6">21) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/the-motivation-for-strategy-d0396049487f" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/the-motivation-for-strategy-d0396049487f" rel="noopener" target="_blank">The Motivation for Strategy</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="230f" name="230f">Insights on the first box in the Strategy Choice Cascade — the Winning Aspiration.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="aa5c" name="aa5c">22) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/the-tragic-futility-of-investing-to-catch-up-aaf4b5c90e0f" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/the-tragic-futility-of-investing-to-catch-up-aaf4b5c90e0f" rel="noopener" target="_blank">The Tragic Futility of Investing to Catch Up</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="adce" name="adce">Investing to catch up competitively has much lower utility than investing to leapfrog competition in order to win.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="2d6c" name="2d6c">23) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/the-role-of-strategy-in-achieving-managerial-effectiveness-688432e020bc" href="https://roger-78069.medium.com/the-role-of-strategy-in-achieving-managerial-effectiveness-688432e020bc" rel="noopener" target="_blank">The Role of Strategy in Achieving Managerial Effectiveness</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="0e45" name="0e45">Managerial effectiveness is aided by clear strategy, not independent of it.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="4e38" name="4e38">24) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/reliability-versus-validity-in-strategy-6df8c9dde8d2" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/reliability-versus-validity-in-strategy-6df8c9dde8d2" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Reliability versus Validity in Strategy</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="03e5" name="03e5">The implications for strategy of two opposing forces in business — producing a consistent replicable outcome and producing an outcome you would actually want.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="29d7" name="29d7">25) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/wheres-the-business-model-in-playing-to-win-33dfb8e87354" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/wheres-the-business-model-in-playing-to-win-33dfb8e87354" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Where’s the Business Model in Playing to Win?</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="e361" name="e361">Your business model is neither independent of nor fits in one box of the Strategy Choice Cascade but is a part of all five boxes.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="2b0c" name="2b0c">26) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/the-shift-from-pre-competitive-to-competitive-c2360bf7594e" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/the-shift-from-pre-competitive-to-competitive-c2360bf7594e" rel="noopener" target="_blank">The Shift from Pre-Competitive to Competitive</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="bc26" name="bc26">The dynamic by which industries shift from a pre-competitive state to a competitive state and implications for strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="b03a" name="b03a">27) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/can-you-be-both-cost-leader-differentiator-1774d5c7ff86" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/can-you-be-both-cost-leader-differentiator-1774d5c7ff86" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Can You Be Both Cost Leader &amp; Differentiator?</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="6a38" name="6a38">For short periods you can be both but in due course, competition will make you choose.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="43fe" name="43fe">28) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/its-time-to-toss-swot-analysis-into-the-ashbin-of-strategy-history-733a0dce4a80" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/its-time-to-toss-swot-analysis-into-the-ashbin-of-strategy-history-733a0dce4a80" rel="noopener" target="_blank">It’s Time to Toss SWOT Analysis in the Ashbin of Strategy History</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="1971" name="1971">The most controversial and widely read of the whole series. Many readers assured me that SWOT isn’t that bad — hardly an endorsement of the tool!</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="12ec" name="12ec">29) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/its-time-to-accept-that-marketing-and-strategy-are-one-discipline-17f0140521c9" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/its-time-to-accept-that-marketing-and-strategy-are-one-discipline-17f0140521c9" rel="noopener" target="_blank">It’s Time to Accept that Marketing and Strategy are One Discipline</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="e914" name="e914">The second most controversial and third most read. Many readers explained that scholarship and current practice disagree with me. But my job is to fix faulty conventional wisdom, not bow to it!</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="8770" name="8770">30) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/manipulation-of-quantities-appreciation-of-qualities-1b166ba9525b" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/manipulation-of-quantities-appreciation-of-qualities-1b166ba9525b" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Manipulation of Quantities &amp; Appreciation of Qualities</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="87a0" name="87a0">The modern strategist needs these two skillsets, but modern education favors manipulation of quantities over appreciation of qualities.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="f636" name="f636">31) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/strategists-stop-obsessing-about-averages-923bc5f57ca0" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/strategists-stop-obsessing-about-averages-923bc5f57ca0" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Strategists: Stop Obsessing about Averages</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="a1a8" name="a1a8">Strategists pay too much attention to averages, which reinforce the status quo, rather than outliers, which give clues to where the future is leading.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="dd39" name="dd39">32) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/what-is-digital-strategy-anyway-fd758e4ef765" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/what-is-digital-strategy-anyway-fd758e4ef765" rel="noopener" target="_blank">What is Digital Strategy, Anyway?</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="9403" name="9403">There are three forms of digital strategy with differing potential for your overall strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="74fa" name="74fa">33) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/overcoming-the-pervasive-analytical-blunder-of-strategists-a5a4c52289b4" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/overcoming-the-pervasive-analytical-blunder-of-strategists-a5a4c52289b4" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Overcoming the Pervasive Analytical Blunder of Strategists</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="556b" name="556b">The analytical blunder strategists make when they take data from the past to make inferences about the future.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="63c5" name="63c5">34) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/your-personal-playing-to-win-strategy-19e0c63aa6c5" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/your-personal-playing-to-win-strategy-19e0c63aa6c5" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Your Personal Playing to Win Strategy</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="73a5" name="73a5">The application of the Playing to Win strategy framework to your personal career.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="dbef" name="dbef">35) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/from-strategy-to-planning-7555234d6cc8" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/from-strategy-to-planning-7555234d6cc8" rel="noopener" target="_blank">From Strategy to Planning</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="5c46" name="5c46">How to productively link your planning to your strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="4f15" name="4f15">36) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/asking-great-strategy-questions-8e58b4aafe76" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/asking-great-strategy-questions-8e58b4aafe76" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Asking Great Strategy Questions</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="e65b" name="e65b">The three classes of questions to review and test strategy; questions about logic, fit, and distinctiveness.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="dfa7" name="dfa7">37) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/its-time-to-accept-that-pay-for-performance-doesn-t-work-716017c62177" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/its-time-to-accept-that-pay-for-performance-doesn-t-work-716017c62177" rel="noopener" target="_blank">It’s Time to Accept that Pay for Performance Doesn’t Work</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="3bdc" name="3bdc">Pay for performance doesn’t help cause productive actions to be taken on strategy; in fact, it causes the opposite.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="676d" name="676d">38) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/playing-to-win-agile-49b5cb2784a4" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/playing-to-win-agile-49b5cb2784a4" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Playing to Win &amp; Agile</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="396f" name="396f">How Agile principles can be integrated with the Playing to Win strategy process.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="2c34" name="2c34">39) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/balancing-exploration-and-exploitation-adb82146837" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/balancing-exploration-and-exploitation-adb82146837" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Balancing Exploration and Exploitation</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="d3c4" name="d3c4">In service of great strategy, one needs to balance exploration of things in which the organization is now not expert with exploitation of things in which the organization is expert.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="5773" name="5773">40) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/the-delusion-of-revenue-forecasting-4262d95bee59" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/the-delusion-of-revenue-forecasting-4262d95bee59" rel="noopener" target="_blank">The Delusion of Revenue Forecasting</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="cd9a" name="cd9a">Revenue forecasting is largely a waste of time because the decision to send revenues to the organization doing the forecasting is completely in customer hands.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="e4db" name="e4db">41) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/its-all-about-confidence-18c508cd4aa1" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/its-all-about-confidence-18c508cd4aa1" rel="noopener" target="_blank">It’s All About Confidence</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="8d0f" name="8d0f">Successful branding is all about building customer confidence.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="9470" name="9470">42) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/can-your-strategy-pass-its-most-important-test-59293df6b3a7" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/can-your-strategy-pass-its-most-important-test-59293df6b3a7" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Can your Strategy Pass its Most Important Test?</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="9493" name="9493">The most important test of your strategy is the can’t/won’t test: are you confident that competitors either can’t or won’t successfully replicate your strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="bec7" name="bec7">43) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/playing-to-win-sales-79460e2fde50" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/playing-to-win-sales-79460e2fde50" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Playing to Win &amp; Sales</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="ad8e" name="ad8e">The important role of sales in strategy and the underappreciation of sales in business school curricula.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="1c01" name="1c01">44) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/diversity-strategy-493bd6cd346a" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/diversity-strategy-493bd6cd346a" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Diversity &amp; Strategy</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="adfe" name="adfe">Diversity of viewpoints is critical to great strategy and that to leverage that diversity, you need to utilize the Integrative Thinking toolbox.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="8f75" name="8f75">45) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/compelling-communication-for-your-strategy-583116ef0334" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/compelling-communication-for-your-strategy-583116ef0334" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Compelling Communication for Your Strategy</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="35bc" name="35bc">In communicating your strategy, less is more, and a picture is worth a thousand words.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="2407" name="2407">46) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/the-proper-role-of-the-chief-strategy-officer-bbc14e3234c5" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/the-proper-role-of-the-chief-strategy-officer-bbc14e3234c5" rel="noopener" target="_blank">The Proper Role of the Chief Strategy Officer</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="2643" name="2643">The proper role of the CSO is to: 1) facilitate the creation of strategy; 2) coordinate the creation of strategy; and 3) ensure the consistency of strategy.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="c8e5" name="c8e5">47) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/should-we-listen-to-customers-7e3c198e4207" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/should-we-listen-to-customers-7e3c198e4207" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Should We Listen to Customers?</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="4a92" name="4a92">The wrong question is whether we should listen to customers. Instead, it should be in what way we should match how we listen to customers with the strategic task at hand.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="a6e3" name="a6e3">48) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/strategy-boards-of-directors-5bb01b73f708" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/strategy-boards-of-directors-5bb01b73f708" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Strategy &amp; Boards of Directors</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="a9cc" name="a9cc">Most management/board relationships are set up for disappointment. The key to success is a better <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">when</em> and a more nuanced <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">what</em>.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="7a0b" name="7a0b">49) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/the-battle-for-the-soul-of-strategy-abf23c7a6d43" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/the-battle-for-the-soul-of-strategy-abf23c7a6d43" rel="noopener" target="_blank">The Battle for the Soul of Strategy</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="8285" name="8285">The battle in strategy theory between the positioning school and the resource-based view of the firm is silly; we need to integrate aspects of both into a better strategy theory.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="aa7d" name="aa7d">50) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/strategy-in-the-face-of-discontinuity-dd9cacdff2b2" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/strategy-in-the-face-of-discontinuity-dd9cacdff2b2" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Strategy in the Face of Discontinuity</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="07d2" name="07d2">The important role that What Would Have to be True can play in helping you determine strategy in the face of discontinuity.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="20cf" name="20cf">51) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/strategy-transformation-4c8d453d40bc" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/strategy-transformation-4c8d453d40bc" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Strategy &amp; Transformation</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="7b1e" name="7b1e">The four keys to transformation success: strategy, patience, resilience and growth.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="f8b6" name="f8b6">52) <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/why-do-strategy-anyway-355e0e760861" href="https://rogermartin.medium.com/why-do-strategy-anyway-355e0e760861" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Why do Strategy, Anyway?</a></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="0162" name="0162">The importance of engaging in strategy in order to learn faster than competitors so as to beat them.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="99fb" name="99fb"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">Where From Here?</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="da6f" name="da6f">That is 85K words of PTW/PI, more than the original <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">Playing to Win</em> book’s 67K words. Two publishers have suggested publishing <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">A Year of Strategy</em> as a book — who would have known, publish it first for free, then as a book? I guess when you are at 256K views (and counting), that is evidence of an audience, so I will do that.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="512b" name="512b">I am going to take a break on the weekly PTW/PIs. I plan to continue writing on Medium, but 1,500–2,000 words/week is a bit too taxing and has crowded out other writing — my HBR Senior Editor, David Champion, is still waiting for my next new magazine piece.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="04d7" name="04d7">My plan is to get even more reader driven. Twenty of the 52 were motivated by reader questions, so readers have already played a big role (thanks!). But I welcome with open arms more ‘what about <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">X</em>/how should I think about <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">Y</em>’ questions. I am planning to broaden from the core Playing to Win theme, so other strategy and/or management questions are entirely welcome. I may do a number of miniseries (say 4–6 pieces rather than 52!) each around a particular theme and have had suggestions already that lend themselves to that format in that the answer has several distinct components and won’t fit into one sub-2000-word piece.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p graf--trailing" id="b3ba" name="b3ba">Thanks for spending <em class="markup--em markup--p-em">A Year of Strategy</em> with me and watch for my next Medium piece within a month.</p></div></div></section>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Battling Our Same-Different Instinct:</title>
<link>https://charltonesque.github.io/medium-archive/posts/2021-10-18_Battling-Our-Same-Different-Instinct--d6356b568ebe.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://charltonesque.github.io/medium-archive/posts/2021-10-18_Battling-Our-Same-Different-Instinct--d6356b568ebe.html</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 13:53:05 +0000</pubDate>
<description>Battling Our Same-Different Instinct: How to Overcome its Harmful Side-Effects Copyright: Roger L. Martin, 2021 Nature has given us many helpful instincts that are intended to keep us safe and healthy</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<section class="section section--body section--first section--last" name="54ae"><div class="section-divider"><hr class="section-divider"/></div><div class="section-content"><div class="section-inner sectionLayout--insetColumn"><h3 class="graf graf--h3 graf--leading graf--title" id="f511" name="f511"><strong class="markup--strong markup--h3-strong">Battling Our Same-Different Instinct:</strong></h3><h4 class="graf graf--h4 graf-after--h3 graf--subtitle" id="50e5" name="50e5"><strong class="markup--strong markup--h4-strong">How to Overcome its Harmful Side-Effects</strong></h4><figure class="graf graf--figure graf-after--h4" id="eed8" name="eed8"><img class="graf-image" data-height="480" data-image-id="1*fHYfex9BvrhvEHX5_m-b4A.gif" data-is-featured="true" data-width="853" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*fHYfex9BvrhvEHX5_m-b4A.gif"/><figcaption class="imageCaption">Copyright: Roger L. Martin, 2021</figcaption></figure><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--figure" id="c11d" name="c11d">Nature has given us many helpful instincts that are intended to keep us safe and healthy. When we touch something that could burn us, we instinctively pull our hand away. When we feel a mosquito biting us, we instinctively swat it. Perhaps most famously, we were given the flight or fight instinct whereby in the face of danger, we choose one of those to reactions without conscious thought.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="abb8" name="abb8">Another somewhat less famous is our instinct for analogy. We instinctively categorize everything we see as either like something we have seen before or not. The best theory (because we can’t know for sure) is that this instinct is there to protect us from anomalous things, for example from harmful things we may ingest. When our ancestors saw a plant or vegetable or fruit that was very similar to ones they had seen before and safely ingested, their instinct told them that this one was safe too. If not, be safe and take a pass.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="30da" name="30da">A modern example of this phenomenon is the Segway, the one-time hot-as-a-pistol, next brilliant forthcoming innovation, funded by hundreds of millions in venture capital, code-named Ginger, and brought to the world by superstar inventor Dean Kaman. The technology was magnificently sophisticated and actually worked as advertised. Nonetheless, Segway <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90517971/exclusive-segway-the-most-hyped-invention-since-the-macintosh-to-end-production" href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90517971/exclusive-segway-the-most-hyped-invention-since-the-macintosh-to-end-production" rel="noopener" target="_blank">ceased production on July 15, 2020</a> having failed utterly and abjectly in its 20-year journey to the ashbin of history.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="b978" name="b978">The problem was that the Segway analogizes to absolutely nothing at all. It is a little wheeled platform, on which you stand upright, largely motionless while moving forward. You didn’t sit as in a car, or peddle as on a bicycle, or steer as with a motorcycle. It was unique — and for the brain, that is simply not a good thing. Think of the last time you saw a rare Segway in use and recall your reaction. For me, it was at an airport and a police officer was patrolling the arrivals level on a Segway. She looked totally weird and laughably geeky on the contraption, and I bet your reaction is the same every time. Our mind simply doesn’t like it because it doesn’t know to what other thing in our mental repertoire to compare it.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="30e6" name="30e6">It isn’t a horseless carriage — i.e., a carriage that has a motor in the front rather than a horse. It isn’t a motorcycle — a bicycle with an engine for propulsion. Or a snowboard — a skateboard for the snow. Or a now-ubiquitous motorized scooter, which looks just like, well, a scooter. Those had powerful positive analogies that enabled the brain to comprehend and categorize this new-but-not-so-new item. Our instincts did not send a ‘watch out, I am uncomfortable’ signal, but rather a ‘yup, got it, we’re OK here’ vibe. That smoothed the adoption processes rather than put roadblocks in their paths.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="4014" name="4014"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">The Cost of Our Instinct</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="2d1b" name="2d1b">Like the rest of our safety driven instincts, this analogy instinct has a value, but it has a cost too, especially in the modern world in which we have other ways of ascertaining the safety of food stuffs. The problem, as with fight or flight, is that it pushes us instinctively to extremes: this is the same, or this is different. And the vast majority of the time, it is somewhere in between. And our instinct causes us to overlook that vast territory to our detriment.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="05cd" name="05cd">For decades, Reuters and Thomson Financial duked it out with Bloomberg for the lucrative global market of leasing desktop terminals that provide live data-feeds for the world’s financial traders, who need the live data to figure out what, how and when to trade. <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://ir.thomsonreuters.com/news-releases/news-release-details/thomson-completes-acquisition-reuters-thomson-reuters-shares" href="https://ir.thomsonreuters.com/news-releases/news-release-details/thomson-completes-acquisition-reuters-thomson-reuters-shares" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Thomson and Reuters even merged in 2008</a> order to better compete with Bloomberg by increasing their scale and then sinking huge investments into making its terminals and feeds as high quality and functional as Bloomberg’s. Yet Thomson Reuters was never been able to carve into the lopsided share lead of Bloomberg and eventually threw in the towel by <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-thomsonreuters-m-a-blackstone/thomson-reuters-closes-deal-with-blackstone-idUSKCN1MB3PY" href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-thomsonreuters-m-a-blackstone/thomson-reuters-closes-deal-with-blackstone-idUSKCN1MB3PY" rel="noopener" target="_blank">selling a majority stake in the business to Blackstone</a>, which in due course <a class="markup--anchor markup--p-anchor" data-href="https://www.nasdaq.com/articles/thomson-reuters-blackstone-affiliates-close-sale-of-refinitiv-to-london-stock-exchange" href="https://www.nasdaq.com/articles/thomson-reuters-blackstone-affiliates-close-sale-of-refinitiv-to-london-stock-exchange" rel="noopener" target="_blank">sold the business to the London Stock Exchange</a>.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="a93b" name="a93b">Why did the attempt to compete with Bloomberg come up so short? Bloomberg really was in a different business — the communications business. Its chat function enabled thousands of traders to communicate with each other about their trading while they traded. It wasn’t about the data feeds; it was about the social network. Bloomberg was and continues to be just plain different, even though from a cursory glance, it looked the same.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="9e8c" name="9e8c">During the 1990’s, Crest lost its long-held market share leadership in toothpaste to rival Colgate. During that period, Crest focused on the difference between two segments of consumers. One segment — Crest’s segment — focused on mouth health, that is protecting against cavities and the dreaded gingivitis referred to in scary terms in advertising copy. The other segment focused on aesthetics — bright, white teeth. To the folks working on the Crest business at the time, it was all about the difference: was a consumer a serious mouth health aficionado or a flighty aesthetics person? However, the folks at eternal rival Colgate came to the conclusion they weren’t so different and in fact virtually all consumers wanted mouth health <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong"><em class="markup--em markup--p-em">and</em></strong> aesthetics and introduced a product that addressed both aspects: Colgate Total. That brilliant product knocked Crest off the toothpaste pedestal and left the Crest folks dazed because they had simply never thought of consumers as being that similar.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="4e7a" name="4e7a">For decades, I have watched this phenomenon of the exaggeration of both similarity (Thomson Reuters versus Bloomberg) and difference (Crest versus Colgate) play out. When we decide a thing is analogous, we are inclined to slip into treating it as ‘the same.’ repeatedly to the detriment of company performance. But if a phenomenon doesn’t fit handily into the ‘same’ category, it tends to get pushed to the absolute far extreme, to ‘different.’ It gets tossed completely out of the ‘same’ category and thrown into a ‘different’ category to be analogized to something else entirely — those aesthetics-oriented toothpaste consumers are like fad dieters; they are superficial and don’t pay attention to fundamentals like proactive health.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="ebfb" name="ebfb">The problem, of course, is that there are differences in sameness and sameness in differences. We get into big trouble the moment we allow our instincts to secretly convince us that a phenomenon is entirely the same or entirely different.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="568c" name="568c"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">Inoculating against the Downsides of Analogy</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="0512" name="0512">Until someone figures out a way to regulate our instinct — and I don’t see that happening anytime soon — we are going to have to accept that it will shove into the center of our consciousness an evaluation of either ‘this is the same’ or ‘this is different.’ Once that reaction hits our consciousness, we have the power to do something useful.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="8963" name="8963"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong"><em class="markup--em markup--p-em">Dealing with the Sameness Message</em></strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="bdca" name="bdca">If our subconscious sends us the message ‘this is the same as that,’ it will provide us very quickly and seamlessly everything that is the same about the thing on which it is focusing. We don’t need help on that front. But we need to do hard conscious work on the differences. It is tremendously important to work through the list of what about the thing in question is different. Line them up against the things that the mind has spewed out instantly as ‘the same.’</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="f704" name="f704">In what ways is this competitor really just not like us? Don’t stop until you have a few ways that it is fundamentally different. Does it actually serve needs in a fundamentally different way like Southwest Airlines? Does it serve an aspect of the customer’s needs that actually we don’t provide like Four Seasons? Does it produce the product in the same way and sell it to the same customers but get it to the customer in a different way like Avon?</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="24e3" name="24e3">In what way is this customer fundamentally different from other customers? Though it may buy the same thing the same way, are they different in terms of the experience they want? Do discount outlet shoppers actually want a different shopping experience like Costco shoppers? Don’t stop until you have something different.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="74b3" name="74b3">Is this employee fundamentally different than other employees? Even though this employee has the same job at the same pay as numerous other employees, is this one meaningfully different because she has worked for only two companies in her 30-year career? Is this employee different because he is a single parent?</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="c1a7" name="c1a7">Perhaps the easiest sameness trap in which to fall is to see the present and future environment in which the company operates as the same as the past. Because the world often changes very slowly, this appears to be a safe assumption — no individual slice of time is very different from the prior slice. It is just like when friends comment on the growth in your daughter and you hadn’t noticed because you see her every day. So, it is important to ask, in the sea of sameness, what made last week or month different than all the previous months?</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="5dea" name="5dea"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong"><em class="markup--em markup--p-em">Dealing with the Difference Message</em></strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="1bff" name="1bff">In parallel fashion, if our subconscious sends us the message ‘this is the different than that,’ it will provide us very quickly and effortlessly everything that is different about the thing on which it is focusing. Hence, we need to do hard conscious work on the sameness; to line up aspects of sameness to go with the differences that our mind has automatically spewed out.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="27bc" name="27bc">Even if this competitor looks different and seems to sell a different product/service, how might it actually meet the same need as us? Do video gaming competitors actually serve the same need for entertainment as us if we are a movie production company? Even if the competitor uses an entirely different process, it is actually producing a very similar product/service? Is Nucor, in fact, as real a steel company as we are? Even if it gets to the customer in a very different way, does Amway really deliver similar value to P&amp;G?</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="d665" name="d665">Even if two sets of customers appear different at first blush, in what ways are they actually quite similar? Do Southwest Airlines customers actually want mostly the same as American/United/Delta customers — a safe, convenient, on-time flying experience? Do Costco customers actually want quality, uniqueness and value nearly as much and in similar fashion to Nordstrom customers? Do Amazon customers think nearly the same about buying stuff as Walmart customers?</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="3938" name="3938">Despite seeming very different on the surface, do Millennials actually want many of the same elements of a relationship with their employer as Baby Boomers? Are blue-collar workers as different from white-collar workers as they are assumed to be at first blush? Might they share deep similarities that need to be considered?</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="14a1" name="14a1">While everything about the environment might be screaming ‘paradigm shift’ or the ‘new normal’ or ‘the end of an era,’ what aspects of it might be remarkably consistent with the past? Might bricks coexist with clicks, localization with globalization, narrowcast with broadcast? What is the sameness to go along with all the difference?</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="5391" name="5391"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">Concluding Thoughts</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p graf--trailing" id="a38e" name="a38e">It is not possible to claim with certainty that had Thomson Reuters paid close attention to the differences with Bloomberg and P&amp;G to the sameness of customer segments while competing with Colgate that their competitive outcomes would have been meaningfully superior. But it is hard to imagine that the dollars would have been invested in the pattern that they were. And while nothing about the future can be certain and competition is never entirely predictable, making a conscious effort to balance the mind’s automatic impulse to race to the extreme of ‘same’ or ‘different’ gives the greatest wealth of insight and information on which to build more robust decisions.</p></div></div></section>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Rule of Fear and the Rules for Fear</title>
<link>https://charltonesque.github.io/medium-archive/posts/2021-10-25_The-Rule-of-Fear-and-the-Rules-for-Fear-796165a28750.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink='true'>https://charltonesque.github.io/medium-archive/posts/2021-10-25_The-Rule-of-Fear-and-the-Rules-for-Fear-796165a28750.html</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 12:46:02 +0000</pubDate>
<description>The Rule of Fear and the Rules for Fear How to Overcome a Central Managerial Challenge Copyright: Roger L. Martin, 2021 What do Humphrey Bogart, John Wayne, Paul Newman, Clint Eastwood, Harrison Ford,</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<section class="section section--body section--first section--last" name="d2aa"><div class="section-divider"><hr class="section-divider"/></div><div class="section-content"><div class="section-inner sectionLayout--insetColumn"><h3 class="graf graf--h3 graf--leading graf--title" id="197f" name="197f"><strong class="markup--strong markup--h3-strong">The Rule of Fear and the Rules for Fear</strong></h3><h4 class="graf graf--h4 graf-after--h3 graf--subtitle" id="b691" name="b691"><strong class="markup--strong markup--h4-strong">How to Overcome a Central Managerial Challenge</strong></h4><figure class="graf graf--figure graf-after--h4" id="330b" name="330b"><img class="graf-image" data-height="480" data-image-id="1*2H5eFsgnJalM0t-bIB2dkQ.gif" data-is-featured="true" data-width="853" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*2H5eFsgnJalM0t-bIB2dkQ.gif"/><figcaption class="imageCaption">Copyright: Roger L. Martin, 2021</figcaption></figure><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--figure" id="7db9" name="7db9">What do Humphrey Bogart, John Wayne, Paul Newman, Clint Eastwood, Harrison Ford, Sylvester Stallone, Arnold Schwarzenegger and Robert Downey, Jr. have in common? The most obvious is that each was the best guarantee of a box office success and highest paid Hollywood actor of their era. Less obvious is that all the characters that they played shared one common defining characteristic — a characteristic that made them irresistibly attractive to audiences. They showed no fear — in fact confidence bordering on cockiness — in situations that would positively overwhelm any normal person with fear — whether Bogart’s Rick Blaine treating the Nazis controlling Casablanca as minor irritations, Harrison’s Han Solo joking while defeating the Evil Empire, or Downey’s Tony Stark wisecracking his way through battles to save the planet.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="5770" name="5770">Some would argue that it was the actor not the character that made them irresistible and famous. Maybe. But remember that a single role, James Bond, played by six different actors across 24 (official Eon-produced) films from 1962 to 2015, generated over $12 billion in inflation-adjusted global box office receipts. And all the Bond actors did pretty much the same thing on screen. Each placidly dispatched his villainous adversaries and immediately thereafter made sure to straighten his tie and adjust his cuffs because 007 must look sharp while saving humanity!</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="b2ca" name="b2ca">We love these fear-impervious characters because at a deep instinctual level, we feel the power of fear. We experience fear of abandonment as children. As we grow, we learn to fear authority figures. When we become adults, we fear the inability to meet obligations like mortgage payments, and kids’ college fees.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="3128" name="3128"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">The Rule of Fear</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="85c1" name="85c1">When fear gets intense enough, our amygdala fires in our reptilian brain stem. The fight or flight mechanism takes over, bypassing the cerebral cortex, and attempts to save the proverbial day. The very prospect, the threat of that instinctive reaction to fear is itself massively fear-inducing.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="e0ed" name="e0ed">When fear is absent, we tell ourselves happy stories that motivate us to achieve aspirational goals. Eighteenth century America revolutionaries told themselves a story about creating a bold new form of democracy and framed a Constitution like no other. John F. Kennedy told Americans a story about putting a man on the moon and NASA went ahead and did it. Late 20th century scientists told a story of what medical insights would be generated if we sequenced the human genome and a decade later the seemingly impossible was done.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="db4a" name="db4a">In sad contrast, when fear replaces confidence, we tell ourselves stories to give us permission to avoid doing the fearfully challenging thing and instead do unconscionable things: the Japanese are such a WWII threat that we must intern all Japanese-Americans; or if we allow gays to serve in the military, ‘unit cohesion’ will fall apart.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="c93f" name="c93f">Narratives are extremely important when it comes to fear. A fear-inducing narrative encourages us to maintain the status quo rather than pursuing beneficial change because change is characteristically fear inducing. Fear of change often trumps fear of a burning — or even smoldering — platform. Even if there are many signs that the platform may be burning, it is often easier to tell ourselves a story that the platform really isn’t burning than to confront the fear of building a new platform.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="852c" name="852c">Nowhere is this truer than in business. To avoid the fear of trying new, challenging things, business leaders tell themselves lots of exculpatory stories. Business leaders are under increasing criticism for declining to make long-term investments. Yet when a bold but risky long-term investment is called for, business leaders tell themselves a story that investors really are only interested in the short-term and will punish anything that deviates from short-term progress. Those interested in environmental sustainability are waging ever-more aggressive battle against corporations. Yet when business leaders feel fear-inducing environmentalist pressure for greater corporate responsibility, they tell themselves a story that deep down inside investors don’t really care about sustainability: they just want performance. When they feel activist pressure for more transparency, they tell themselves that the more data they reveal, the more vulnerable they become. When they are pressured to ensure ethical sourcing, they tell themselves that taking responsibility for their entire value chain is too high a risk.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="cb64" name="cb64">Consequently, a central imperative for leaders is the management of fear: fear at two levels — their own fear and fear in their teams. The task is not to eliminate it but rather to maintain it at a level that motivates action but doesn’t trigger the amygdala. And their key tool is narrative. To manage fear productively, the leader needs to transform the narrative, both for self and for followers.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="32dc" name="32dc"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">Fear at Unilever</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="314c" name="314c">When Paul Polman took over as CEO in 2009, fear ruled Unilever. He took its reins in the depth of the global financial crisis — a calamity that induced fear in the whole world. On top of that, Unilever was doing particularly badly — its brands losing share, its profitability shrinking, and its relevance dissipating.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="2377" name="2377">But Polman managed his own fears. He understood the downward spiral that fear caused and that gave him the fortitude to manage the fear rather than fall prey to it. Instead he told a different story; a narrative of a firm dedicated to the longer term. He announced that Unilever would henceforth stop quarterly reporting and stop giving guidance. It wasn’t easy. But by managing his own fear, Polman was able to author an entirely different narrative.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="6520" name="6520">While Unilever was in an inherently fear-generating position, backed by a fear-inducing narrative, due to the combination of its performance and the global financial crisis, and Polman had a set of well-established exculpatory stories to rely on to continue the status quo, he managed his own fear by reframing the fear-producing elements of his environment a positive, opportunity-laden narrative. That enabled him to lead Unilever in a radical and exemplary direction that has made it perhaps the most important innovator in corporate and social responsibility in the entire universe of global companies. Perhaps most importantly, he has provided a calming story for other CEOs to help manage their fears.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="b995" name="b995"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">Fear at Lego</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="ce4d" name="ce4d">In 2004, fear ran high and deep in Billund, Denmark. The bucolic town of 6000 inhabitants in the middle of Danish farm country housed one of the world’s iconic brands: Lego. But in 2003, the privately-owned company run by third generation family member Kjeld Kristiansen had lost a staggering US$240 million on US$1 billion of sales. While the company had grown spectacularly and profitably under his leadership, in recent days, it had stretched too far geographically, and diversified too much into theme parks, games and electronics. The overexpansion had put the venerable company on the verge of bankruptcy — a thought that terrified the board, senior management, employees, Billund’s citizens, and, given the importance to its export economy, Denmark itself.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="e966" name="e966">Seeing the need for a fundamental turnaround, Kristiansen turned to reins over to Jørgen Vig Knudstorp, who knew that calming fear was as big a job as staunching the financial hemorrhaging. When employees are fearful, the flight reaction translates into putting down their tools in both conscious and subconscious ways. They were paralyzed. They wanted to help but had no idea how they would contribute to a turnaround. Knudstorp knew that he had to attack the fear by creating a story of success and starting to produce outcomes that would provide data that reinforced the story.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="d42f" name="d42f">His story to the company was that the core business was great — consumers and retailers loved the core product and wanted it to succeed. He just needed to get the company back to its basics to restore its health and momentum. That meant cutting product lines, stopping the diversification, selling the theme parks to Blackstone Group, and, sadly, shrinking the workforce by nearly half.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="8c0e" name="8c0e">The story calmed fears and the actions turned around the company, setting it on course for a decade of uninterrupted growth that by 2014 propelled Lego past Hasbro and Mattel to become the largest toy company in the world — and the most profitable.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="09f6" name="09f6"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">The Rules for Fear</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="ba12" name="ba12">The successful surmounting of fear by Polman and Knudstorp, and others who I have studied, suggests five Fear Rules for leaders in order to manage fear to a level that is motivating and not paralyzing.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="68ac" name="68ac"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong"><em class="markup--em markup--p-em">Rule One: Eternal Vigilance is the Price of Freedom</em></strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="635f" name="635f">Fear is not something that can be eliminated. It is always lurking. It is a human instinct that is there to protect us. Even though there was little fear at Lego in the decade before 2003, it reached a fevered pitch in the space of one year. Watch for it as it rises in you or your team. Dealing with it is urgent business — not something that can be put off. Fear generates actions that produce more fear and an acceleration of the damage. When it comes to fear, <strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong"><em class="markup--em markup--p-em">now </em></strong>is the time to work on it.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="21a4" name="21a4"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong"><em class="markup--em markup--p-em">Rule Two: Your Fear is Job #1</em></strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="970d" name="970d">Leaders won’t be able to help their team overcome their fear if they are overcome themselves. Hence the Fear Rule for leaders is to work on overcoming your own fear yourself before you even think about attempting to manage the fear of your team. And if you can’t generate a positive narrative to help you overcome your own fear, you should step aside because you are incapable of productive leadership at that critical time.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="b10c" name="b10c"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong"><em class="markup--em markup--p-em">Rule Three: The Basis of Fear is a Narrative</em></strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="c239" name="c239">Fear is generated by stories we tell ourselves. We take data-points and assemble them into narratives that help us understand the world. But sometimes, we assemble those data-points into scary stories. As a leader, you must understand each person’s story to understand every person’s fear because their narrative drives their actions. If you don’t understand the story, you won’t understand the fear. Additionally, if you deny the story, you send the fear underground where it is harder to counteract.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="3ddb" name="3ddb"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong"><em class="markup--em markup--p-em">Rule Four: The Antidote for Fear is a Happy Story</em></strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="9950" name="9950">To conquer fear, a leader needs to craft a compellingly happy story. That narrative needs to build a bridge for the organization from the scary story to a happier place. If it is entirely independent of the scary story, it won’t be credible and compelling. Both Polman and Vig Knudstorp reframed the scary story as a set of data points that could be migrated to a happy narrative and reduced fear to a level that enabled employees to work with enthusiasm. But of course, Knudstorp and Polman had to overcome their own fear by telling themselves a happy story of their ability to lead their respective organizations in a way that caused the happy story to become true — and both were able to do just that.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="2a60" name="2a60"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong"><em class="markup--em markup--p-em">Rule Five: Tell the Happy Story Over and Over</em></strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="e441" name="e441">In the face of the fearful story, it takes the happy story some time to sink in and truly replace the fearful story as the dominant narrative. The replacement doesn’t happen with one telling. For this reason, it is critical to keep reinforcing the happy story until it, not the fearful one that preceded it, is second nature. For leaders, this means telling the happy story until they are absolutely sick of hearing themselves talk. Only then is it likely to be the core story across their organization.</p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p" id="464c" name="464c"><strong class="markup--strong markup--p-strong">Concluding Thoughts</strong></p><p class="graf graf--p graf-after--p graf--trailing" id="17fe" name="17fe">Neither the world nor any organization in it can be stripped entirely of fear. It is a naturally occurring aspect of life on the planet. Some amount of it is motivational. But too much is counterproductive, even debilitating. A key task of leaders is to recognize as and when fear has risen to an intense enough level in themselves and their teams to take action — first by managing their own fear and then by managing their teams’ fears.</p></div></div></section>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>